Guide to the Randy Riddle Collection of Race Records and Radio Programs, 1920s-1965 RL.01090
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Randy Riddle Collection of Race records and Radio Programs
1920s-1965
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Riddle, Randy (collector)
RL.01090
5 Linear Feet
Randy Riddle is an Academic Technology Consultant with the Center for Instructional Technology (CIT) at Duke University, and a collector of race records and radio programs. Collection includes 12 inch and 18 inch vinyl, acetate, and lacquer race records and radio programs from the 1920s through the 1960s.
200 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Original recordings are closed to researchers.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Some electronic use copies are available in the collection. Otherwise, Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Randy Riddle Collection of Race Records and Radio Programs was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010 and 2011.
Historical Note
The music and recordings in this collection were acquired and donated by Randy Riddle, an Academic Technology Consultant for the Center for Instructional Technology (CIT) at Duke University. The collection includes both race records and radio programs.
Race records is a phrase describing 78 rpm gramophone records made for and by African Americans during the early 20th century. These recordings typically contained blues, gospel, jazz, or comedy programs targeting African American audiences. Recording companies marketing race records included Okeh Records, Emerson Records, Vocalion Records, and the Victor Talking Machine Company, among others. By the 1960s, race records on the Billboard chart had been replaced by the phrase rhythm and blues.
The radio programs in this collection are a variety of recordings from numerous shows that aired in the 1930s through the 1960s. Some of these discs are the only known copies of the program in existence.
Collection Overview
The Randy Riddle Collection includes two series: Race Records and Radio Programs. The Race Records series consists of thirty-four 12 inch (78 rpm) gramophone records and one 45 rpm record. Each includes two songs, one per side, by an artist. Most of the records are in good or excellent condition. Artists represented in this collection are: Emitt Slay Trio, Bert Williams, Moran and Mack, The Orioles, Billy Wright, Johnney Rebel, The Couplings, Bob Howard and his Boys, The Midnighters, Jimmy Bowen with the Rhythm Orchids, The Clovers, Chuck Miller, Miles Davis and his Orchestra, The Original Casuals featuring Gary Mears, Eunice Davis with Orchestra, Ivory Joe Hunter, Cab Calloway and his Orchestra, Howlin Wolf, Varetta Dillard, Louis Armstrong and his Orchestra, Louis Jordan and his Tympany Five, Carson Robinson, Young Jessie, Chuck Webb and his Orchestra, Socko Underwood, Brownie McGhee, and Bull Moose Jackson and his Buffalo Bearcats.
The Race Records series has not been converted to a digital format, meaning that there are no use copies available at this time. Use copies must be made before researchers can access this material. Contact the Rubenstein Library with questions.
The Radio Programs series includes both 12 inch (78 rpm) records and 16 inch transcription discs, including vinyl, lacquer, and acetate records. Programs include recordings of both original on-air broadcasts as well as rebroadcasts by organizations such as the Armed Forces Radio Service. Frequently, the discs include only excerpts or pieces of a program, and program runs are not complete (many include only one or two episodes). Titles in the collection are: This is My Best (Globe Theater); Lest We Forget; Pick and Pat; Southland Echoes; Harlem Hospitality Club; lacquer records from WREN in Lawrence, Kansas; the Bea Kalmus Show; Choose a Song Partner; Americans at Work; Any Bonds Tonight; American Family Robinson; a Townsend Plan filmstrip soundtrack; Twenty Questions; Monticello Party Line; Coke Club; Plantation Echoes; Behind the Scenes in Hollywood; Your Home Front Reporter; Billie Burke; Aladdin Lamp; America's Famous Fathers; Mad Hatterfields; Supper Club; Uncle Remus; Dwight Eisenhower campaign special; Christmas Seal; and special episodes from the March of Dimes and American Cancer Society fundraising drives.
The Radio Programs series has digital use copies available, including high-resolution scans of some records' labels. Original transcription discs are CLOSED to use. Please contact the Rubenstein Library with questions on how to access the digital files for these programs.
Riddle, Randy (collector)
- Race Records, 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Series consists of 78 rpm gramophone records, including songs by Louis Armstrong, Bert Williams, and The Midnighters. Includes one 45 rpm record by Johnney Rebel.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials requires production of listening copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - Emitt Slay Trio (Box 1)
    - My Kind of Woman (Box 1)
    - Brotherly Love (Box 1)
  - Bert Williams
    - Unexpectedly (Box 1)
    - Brother Low Down (Box 1)
    - Unlucky Blues (Box 1)
    - Ten Little Bottles (Box 1)
    - The Moon Shines on the Moonshine (Box 1)
    - Somebody (Box 1)
    - Get Up (Box 1)
    - I Want to Know Where Tosti Went (Box 1)
    - When I Return (Box 1)
    - O Death Where is Thy Sting (Box 1)
  - Moran and Mack
    - Two Black Crows (Parts 1 and 2) (Box 1)
  - The Orioles
    - Forgive and Forget (Box 1)
    - So Much (Box 1)
  - Billy Wright
    - Keep Your Hands on Your Heart (Box 1)
    - Mean Old Wine (Box 1)
  - Johnney Rebel
    - Kajun Klu Klux Klan (Box 1)
    - Looking for a Handout (Box 1)
  - The Couplings (Box 2)
    - Young Dove's Calling (Box 2)
    - I Can See (Box 2)
  - Bob Howard and his Boys
    - If You're a Viper (Box 2)
    - Raggedy But Right (Box 2)
  - The Midnighters
    - Let Me Hold Your Hand (Box 2)
    - Ooh Bah Baby (Box 2)
  - Jimmy Bowen with the Rhythm Orchids
    - Don't Tell Me Your Troubles (Box 2)
    - Ever Since That Night (Box 2)
  - The Clovers
    - Love, Love, Love (Box 2)
    - Your Tender Lips (Box 2)
    - Crawlin' (Box 2)
    - Yes, It's You (Box 2)
    - I've Got My Eyes on You (Box 2)
    - Your Cash Ain't Nothin' But Trash (Box 2)
  - Chuck Miller
    - The House of Blue Lights (Box 2)
    - Can't Help Wonderin' (Box 2)
  - Miles Davis and his Orchestra
    - Move (Box 2)
    - Budo (Box 2)
  - The Original Casuals, Featuring Gary Mears
    - It's Been a Long Time Girl (Box 2)
    - Three Kisses Past Midnight (Box 2)
  - Eunice Davis with Orchestra
    - My Beat is 125th Street (Box 2)
    - Go To Work Pretty Daddy (Box 2)
  - Ivory Joe Hunter
    - Since I Met You Baby (Box 2)
    - You Can't Stop This Rocking and Rolling (Box 2)
  - Cab Calloway and his Orchestra
    - Chattanooga Choo Choo (Box 2)
    - Take the A Train (Box 2)
  - Howlin Wolf
    - I Asked For Water (Box 2)
    - So Glad (Box 2)
  - Varetta Dillard (Box 3)
    - Mercy, Mister Percy (Box 3)
    - No Kinda Good, No How (Box 3)
  - Louis Armstrong and his Orchestra
    - On the Sentimental Side (Box 3)
    - It's Wonderful (Box 3)
    - On the Sunny Side of the Street (Box 3)
    - Satchel Mouth Swing (Box 3)
  - Louis Jordan and his Tympany Five
    - The Chicks I Pick are Slender and Tender and Tall (Box 3)
    - What's the Use of Getting Sober (Box 3)
  - Carson Robinson
    - Mussolini's Letter to Hitler (Box 3)
    - Hitler's Reply to Mussolini (Box 3)
  - Young Jessie
    - Shuffle in the Gravel (Box 3)
    - Make Believe (Box 3)
  - Chuck Webb and his Orchestra
    - I Got a Guy (Box 3)
    - Harlem Congo (Box 3)
  - Socko Underwood
    - You've Got Another Pal (Box 3)
    - I'm Only a Convict's Wife (Box 3)
  - The Midnighters
    - That Woman (Box 3)
    - Give It Up (Box 3)
  - Brownie McGhee
    - Auto Mechanic Blues (Box 3)
    - Country Boy Boogie (Box 3)
  - Bull Moose Jackson and his Buffalo Bearcats
    - All My Love Belongs to You (Box 3)
    - I Want a Bowlegged Woman (Box 3)
- Radio Programs, 10 boxes
  Series includes transcription records and 78 rpm records of radio programs that aired throughout the United States between the 1930s and the 1960s.
  Original audiovisual materials in this collection are closed to researchers and should not be recalled from the LSC. Digital copies of this material are available, on Duke's servers and in Box 13. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - The Bea Kalmus Show, January 13, 1960 (Box 4)
    One 12" lacquer disc, very good condition. Excerpt from a disc jockey program by Bea Kalmus, the first female DJ on commercial radio. The guest on this show is Otis Blackwell.
  - Any Bonds Tonight and Americans at Work, 1940s (Box 4)
    Six 12" lacquer 78 rpm discs, excellent condition. Contains 3 fifteen minute programs aired during World War II, aimed to raise funds for War Bonds while boosting workers' morale. Records were recorded for Carl E. Payne of the Oscar W. Hedstrom Corp., who gives short talks about labor and workers joining together for the war effort. WCFL was owned by the Chicago Federation of Labor.
  - Choose a Song Partner, 1947 (Box 5)
    Five 16" vinyl discs, excellent condition. Program from circa 1947, targeting women, featuring comedienne and actress Beryl Vaughn and vocalist Don Moreland. Produced by Eugenia Price Productions, and sponsored by Formfit Life Bras and Life Girdles. Includes Programs 1-2 and 5-12, circa 1947. Record sleeve samples are included at the end of the run.
  - Harlem Hospitality Club, 1947 (Box 5)
    Two 16" vinyl discs, excellent condition. Originally broadcast on Mutual, these discs were rebroadcast by Armed Forces Radio Service. The program was a half-hour of rhythm and blues music, including audience participation, featuring Willie Bryant and guests such as Amanda Randolph. One of the few examples from the period of network radio programs aimed at African American audiences.
  - Townsend Plan (filmstrip soundtrack) (Box 5)
    One 16" vinyl disc, excellent condition. Filmstrip soundtrack (the filmstrip has been lost) promoting and advertising the Townsend Plan, an alternative to Social Security that was lobbied for through the 1930s.
  - Twenty Questions (Box 5)
    Two 16" vinyl discs, excellent condition. Program was a radio show where listeners submitted ideas to try and stump the panel. One of the panelists, Robert Van Deventer, also known as Bobby McGuire, was a Duke alumnus. No dates are included on the labels. Program aired between 1946 and 1954.
  - Records from WREN (Lawrence, Kansas), 1940s (Box 6)
    Eighteen 16" lacquer discs, poor to good condition. A set of discs thrown away from WREN in Lawrence, Kansas. Most feature parts of programs by a local Western swing group, The Range Riders. Also contain excerpts from the 1946-1947 series Ladies Be Seated. Most programs include appearances by an actress in character as the sponsor, Aunt Jemima. Record sleeve samples are included at the end of the run.
  - Pick and Pat, 1937-1938 and undated (Box 7)
    Nine 16" lacquer discs, poor to good condition. Series was broadcast on CBS in the late 1930s, featuring Blackface comedy team Pick Padgett and Pat Malone. These discs contain significant parts of several episodes, and were made as air checks by WABC radio. Record sleeve samples are included at the end of the run.
  - American Family Robinson (Box 7)
    Fourteen 16" acetate discs, excellent condition. Dramatic serial produced around 1935 by the National Association of Manufacturers as part of an effort to combat the New Deal; characters frequently drop plugs for conservative ideas. NAM originally approached NBC and CBS about carrying the series, but the networks declined. Instead, NAM syndicated the show to about 300 stations under the moniker National Industry Council. The show was the subject of Congressional hearings by members who felt the program was misleading. Includes Programs 38-43, 48-63, 68-71, and 84-85. Record sleeve samples are included at the end of the run.
  - Southland Echoes, 1949 (Box 8)
    Ten 16" vinyl discs, excellent condition. Produced by Nelson Chesman Company, Chattanooga, Tennessee, and sponsored by Black Draught Laxative and Cardui. 15 minute shows consist of gospel songs by the Homeland Harmony Quartet, the Jones Sisters, and Blackface comedians Jam-Up and Honey. Includes Programs 5-6, 17-20, and 23-36. Record sleeve samples are included at the end of the run.
  - Globe Theater (Box 8)
    One 16" vinyl disc. Armed Forces Radio Service rebroadcast of Norman Corwin-produced series, This is My Best. Program 166: features the original cast of Porgy and Bess, performing a half-hour adaptation of the musical.
  - Lest We Forget, 1940s
    Nine 16" vinyl discs. The series was created to promote tolerance, and the programs feature stories about prejudice based on religion, race, or ethnicity. Produced and syndicated in the late 1940s by the Institute for Democratic Education. Includes Programs 9-10, 14-21, 27-28, and 31-36.
    - 9: Liberty Inn (Box 8)
    - 10: Sky View (Box 8)
    - 14: The Lesson (Box 8)
    - 15: The Outcasts (Box 8)
    - 16: Rosika, The Rose (Box 8)
    - 17: My Little Boy (Box 8)
    - 18: Yes, Your Honesty (Box 8)
    - 19: Seasoned Timber (Box 8)
    - 20: That Greek Dog (Box 8)
    - 21: Birthday Gift (Box 8)
    - 27: Face to Face (Box 8)
    - 28: Blow that Whistle (Box 8)
    - 31: Sheriff Matt Blake (Box 8)
    - 32: Hey, Cabbie (Box 8)
    - 33: One Small Voice (Box 8)
    - 34: Chain Reaction (Box 8)
    - 35: Arrow in the Air (Box 8)
    - 36: The Carolina Kid (Box 8)
  - Your Home Front Reporter, 1943 (Box 9)
    Eleven 16" vinyl discs. A series run on CBS during WWII each weekday. Each half-hour show, sponsored by the Owens Illinois Glass Company and produced by the D'Arcy Advertising Company, includes vocalists Frank Parker and Met Opera star Eleanor Steber early in her career. The main body of each show is a commentary by Fletcher Wiley, who came to prominence in the 1930s in Southern California talking in a folksy style to women about issues they were interested in. Wiley's commentaries focus on the warfront at home and current news on rationing and other issues of interest to the WWII housewife. Some of the later shows in this disc series have reporter Don Pryor filling in for Fletcher Wiley. These are the only surviving episodes of the series and the discs appear to have been especially prepared for the sponsor, Owens Illinois. The donation includes the original shipping labels (the paper containers had deteriorated) where the discs were sent to an executive at the company. Shipping labels are housed in Box 13.
    - May 10, 1943 (Box 9)
      First program in the series. Fletcher Wiley talks at the beginning of the show about the purpose of the program, then offers a commentary on politeness and another on the many uses of the soybean. Frank Parker performs "Begin the Beguine" and Eleanor Steber sings "Carry Me Back to Old Virginia"; they perform a duet, "Dearly Beloved". The announcer is Ben Grauer; features the David Brookman Orchestra. Notes: This may be a rehearsal recording since it runs over 30 minutes (others in the series run 25 minutes). Scratch on second side at beginning for first three minutes or so.
    - May 11, 1943 (Box 9)
      Second program in the series. Fletcher Wiley discusses why we should not get too excited about good news from the war front since the end of the war may be some time away. He also mentions that new shipments of alarm clocks are coming on the market. Eleanor Steber sings "Just a Song at Twilight"; Frank Parker performs "The Night is Young, And You're So Wonderful"; Steber and Parker sing the duet "Why Do I Love You?". With announcer Hugh Conover and the David Brookman Orchestra.
    - May 12, 1943 (Box 9)
      Third program in the series. Fletcher Wiley comments on taking care of your car for the war effort, women going on blind dates, and other topics. Frank Parker sings "One Alone"; Eleanor Steber performs "In the Glow". The David Brookman Orchestra plays the "Missouri Waltz".
    - June 10, 1943 (Box 9)
      Program 24 in the series. Fletcher Wiley reminds everyone to apply for their new ration books and gives a talk about gossip. Frank Parker performs "Mother of Mine"; Eleanor Steber sings "Bartlett's Dream"; Steber and Parker sing the duet "'Neath the Harvest Moon". With the David Brookman Orchestra and announcer Hugh Conover.
    - June 14, 1943 (Box 9)
      Program 26 in the series. Fletcher Wiley talks about a new "welding" sewing machine you can buy after the War if you buy and save up your War Bonds and offers a commentary on keeping a positive attitude and "getting along" with what's available in wartime. Frank Parker sings "Drink to Me Only With Thine Eyes"; Parker and Eleanor Stebel perform "If You Were the Only Girl in the World" and Stebel sings Gershwin's "Summertime". With the David Brookman Orchestra and announcer Hugh Conover.
    - September 20, 1943 (Box 9)
      Program 96 in the series. Fletcher Wiley's commentary is on why service flags are a symbol of democracy and he does some remarks on making the most of clothes during wartime. Phil Hanna and Diana Gayle sing "Tip Toe Through the Tulips" and "The West, A Nest, and You"; Phil Regan sings "Boy of Mine". Wilbur Hatch conducts the orchestra.
    - September 29, 1943 (Box 9)
      Program 103 in the series. Don Regan looks at stories in the news about love during wartime, including a woman in Idaho arranging a marriage by proxy with her beau in England, and other lighter news items. He also does a commentary on travel during wartime and how useful a good suitcase can be. Eleanor Steber sings Gershwin's "Summertime" and "Alice Blue Gown"; Walter Castle performs "Through the Years". Phil Regan sings "Take Me in Your Arms". Steber and Castle sing "Make Believe" from "Showboat". With the David Brookman Orchestra, Hugh Conover announcing.
    - October 4, 1943 (Box 9)
      Program 106 in the series. Not auditioned.
    - October 5, 1943 (Box 9)
      Program 107 in the series. Not auditioned.
    - October 8, 1943 (Box 9)
      Program 110 in the series. Not auditioned.
    - October 13, 1943 (Box 9)
      Program 113 in the series. Not auditioned.
  - Plantation Echoes, 1932 (Box 9)
    One 16" shellac disc, broken. An early 1930s program syndicated by Transco. It features an almost all-Black cast in stories set on an "old South" plantation and the stories include Black songs and spirituals. The plot of the story concerns a runaway slave. This and one other program are the only surviving episodes of the series (the other is in private hands). This disc, for Episode 9, is broken into three pieces.
  - Billie Burke Show, 1946 (Box 10)
    One 16" lacquer disc. One of three episodes of this unusual situation comedy in existence. Originally heard on CBS on Saturday mornings for a season or so following the long-running children's program Let's Pretend. The show, sponsored by Listerine Toothpaste and Tooth Powder, stars Billie Burke, better known for her role as Glenda in The Wizard of Oz. The show seems to be aimed at children and their mothers, with storylines about Billie's family getting in awkward situations and learning some kind of lesson.
    The episode in this collection aired April 27, 1946. When a tramp shows up at her back door begging for food, Billie teaches her brother Julius a little lesson about charity. Marked "Copy" on the disc label. Note that there's an odd transition between the sides - side one cuts off suddenly, but the second side is faded in.
  - Armed Forces Radio Service: Supper Club, 1945
    One 16" vinyl disc. Two programs in the series "Chesterfield Supper Club": this is the version of the program heard on AFRS with the commercials and sponsor information omitted. Featuring Perry Como and sponsored by Chesterfield cigarettes, this was usually a quarter-hour program of vocal music. However, some were done in the style of minstrel show with guests Blackface comedians Pick and Pat heard with Como in the role of interlocutor. A handful of these shows survive in other collections, but this particular copy is unique.
    - Program 85: May 23, 1945 (Box 10)
      Originally broadcast as Chesterfield Supper Club on NBC. With Perry Como, Martin Block, Pick and Pat The Satisfiers, Mary Ashworth, Ted Steele and His Orchestra. Opening tune is the theme song of "Pick and Pat"'s radio program. Show is done in the style of a minstrel show. Como sings "Mammy" as the opening tune. Previously lost.
    - Program 86: May 30, 1945 (Box 10)
      Originally broadcast as "Chesterfield Supper Club" on NBC. With Perry Como, Martin Block, Pick and Pat The Satisfiers, Mary Ashworth, Ted Steele and His Orchestra. Opening tune is "Carry On, Brother, Carry On." Previously lost.
  - Uncle Remus, 1947 (Box 10)
    Three 16" discs (2 vinyl, 1 lacquer). Four programs (1, 11, 2, and "Mud Pies") in the series Uncle Remus featuring Jimmie Scribner. Syndicated during the Christmas season in 1947, the show features Scribner, a white actor, playing all the roles in the program. Scribner was known for doing a Black-themed radio soap where he played all the characters, "The Johnson Family". This show is a real oddity - it appeared to have run only one month and was withdrawn. Scribner re-recorded the shows with the same scripts, omitting any references to Uncle Remus and changing the name of the character to "Sleepy Joe". This might have been because Song of the South came out in 1947 and Disney might have objected to use of the Remus name on the series.
  - America's Famous Fathers, circa 1941
    One 16" vinyl disc. An obscure syndicated show from circa 1941 that features Howard Lindsay, star of Life with Father, discussing fatherhood with some famous guests. The programs feature Lowell Thomas and, in the other show, Col. Theodore Roosevelt and Mrs. John Phillips Marquand. Roosevelt is a highlight of the show, recalling stories about his father, President Theodore Roosevelt. No other shows in the series survive.
    - Episode 12 (Box 10)
      Features Lowell Thomas telling a dramatized story about two men that are stranded after their airplane crashes. Ray Green is the announcer.
    - Episode 24 (Box 10)
      Col. Theodore Roosevelt and the wife of author John Phillips Marquand debate the role of fathers in the household. Roosevelt relates some fun and interesting stories about his own father, President Roosevelt. Howard Lindsay, who normally was host of the show, was ill and unable to appear, so announcer Ray Green conducts the interview.
  - The Coke Club, July 19, 1946-September 6, 1946 (Box 10)
    Three 16" vinyl discs. Six episodes (Programs 380C, 381C, 406C, 408C, 410C, 411C, 413C, 415C) of a quarter-hour syndicated music show sponsored by Coca-Cola and produced by D'Arcy Advertising. Features Morton Downey doing popular tunes and sometimes religious numbers. Some shows also include a "salute" to different towns each week with a story about an interesting person in the town apparently submitted by the local Coca-Cola bottler. Coca-Cola themed labels on the discs.
  - Christmas Seal Campaign, 1950 (Box 10)